You were involved in the capture of Abu
Zuba.
>> I was. Uh and tell me about that. How it
happened.
>> It was quite a long process. Uh we had
information that Abu Zubedo was
somewhere in Pakistan uh in either
Fisabad or Lahore. And we undertook a uh
a weeksl long month-long uh
investigation. We were able to narrow
his location down to more than a dozen
possibilities. and working with the
Pakistani government and with the FBI,
we we raided each one of those sites and
found him in one of the in one of the
houses.
>> And how were you able to focus in on
where he was?
>> It was very difficult, but it was it was
really a combination of of things. It
was it was a wide variety of sources
reporting on possibilities of where
either he might be located or where uh
others might be located who would know
of his whereabouts. We decided not to
take the chance and and just hit one or
two sites, fearing that uh word would
get back to him and he'd have a chance
to to run off and and go deeper
underground. So, we elected to hit all
the sites at the same time at the same
night. And we're lucky enough that he
was in one of them.
>> And how many uh people did that involve?
A big operation, I think.
>> Yeah, just on the American side, it was
about three dozen people. There were a
lot of uh there were a lot of heroes
that night. People worked hard and
worked closely together and it worked.
And why were you uh focused on him?
>> We were told at the time, well, we had a
lot of information on Abu Zuba going
back into the 90s. He was one of the
financiers of the September 11th
attacks. He was a logistics chief uh of
al-Qaeda and we knew that he was close
to Bin Laden, although not colllocated.
Obviously, we know that we knew at the
time that he had aligned to Mid Laden
and we thought that if we could capture
him, it would deal a significant blow to
the al-Qaeda leadership. And he was in
Pakistan.
>> He was in Feist Labad, Pakistan.
Correct.
>> And how long had he been there?
>> We're not sure. It it seemed to us he
admitted to having been there a week. We
thought he was probably there more like
2 or 3 weeks.
>> And when was this?
>> This was in March of 2002.
>> So you'd been looking for him since
September 11th essentially.
>> We had We had indeed.
>> And uh when when the catch was made,
when you caught up with him, he hit the
right place. What happened there? Did he
resist?
>> He resisted. There was a shootout. The
Pakistanis were the first uh inside the
door and he stabbed a Pakistani
policeman in the neck. Uh we feared at
the time that he that he had died.
Things were happening so quickly it was
confusing and uh the Pakistani
authorities told us initially that the
man had died. He turned out to just have
been wounded. But then Abu Zubeda uh
went up to the roof of his house and
tried to jump to the roof of the
neighboring house. He exchanged in a in
a gun battle with the Pakistani police
down below and he was shot three times
and then dropped from the roof of the
house onto the ground. He was almost
killed. And later that night, one of the
doctors, the Pakistani doctors who was
treating him told me that he had never
seen wounds so severe where the patient
had lived.
>> And what happened to him after you
caught up with him on?
>> Well, we took him to a hospital for for
emergency uh treatment. The hospital in
Vice Labad was uh was just a a terrible
place. So we evacuated him to a military
hospital in Lahore and uh the director
of central intelligence George Tennant
immediately got on the phone to John's
Hopkins University and asked if they
could send a trauma surgeon to Pakistan.
So that trauma surgeon got on a plane, a
private plane, flew directly to the base
and uh I guess it was about 24 hours
after the shooting uh he was able to
begin treating Abu Zabeta.
>> And what was the nature of his wounds?
>> He was shot in the thigh, the groin, and
the stomach with an AK-47
>> and barely survived.
>> Barely survived. One of the things that
sticks in my mind uh from those those
days and nights was how much blood he
lost. There was blood everywhere. It was
all over him. It was all over the bed.
It pulled underneath the bed. It was all
over us every time we had to move him.
It was really an incredible amount of
blood that he lost.
>> After you captured him, what was your
security like to keep him under uh lock
and key?
>> The security was I tore up a sheet and
tied him to the bed.
>> You did?
>> Yeah. That was about all we could do in
those initial hours. Um the idea was we
wanted to get him to a to a place where
he would be safe, where he could recover
from his wounds and where we could begin
interviewing him. But uh the idea was uh
just to keep everybody not with us or
his medical team away from him. And
that's what we did. There was a group of
nurses and he had the Pakistani military
doctor uh doing everything he could to
help him. But otherwise, it was me and
it was a small group of uh of CIA and
FBI people who just kept 24/7 eyes on
him.
>> So, you were in the room that whole
time?
>> Yeah. And in fact, I was the first
person that spoke to him when he came
out of his coma.
>> And what did you say?
>> He asked me, well, first I went up to
him and I I asked him in Arabic what his
name was and he shook his head and I
asked him again in Arabic and then he
answered me in English and he said that
he would not speak to me in God's
language. Uh, and then I said, "That's
okay. We know who you are." And then he
asked me to smother him with a pillow
and I said, "No, no, we have we have
plans for you." Um, and I encouraged him
from the very beginning to cooperate and
to tell us what he knew. Frankly, there
were lives at stake and we knew that he
was the biggest fish that we had caught.
We knew he was full of information and
uh and we wanted to get it. One of the
reasons why it was of such uh importance
to us that night is the room where where
he was when the raid began had a table
in it and on the table Abu Zuba and two
other men were building a bomb. The
soldering iron was still hot and they
had the plans for uh for a school on the
table. So we knew that there were u
immediate threats that he could uh he
could help us with. A school where
>> in Lahore in Lahore Pakistan
>> a Pakistani school
>> we think it was the American school or
the British school I guess it was not
the American school.
>> So you felt that he was he was very
current. He knew what was going on.
>> Very current on top of of the current
threat information. He he was so well
tied into the al-Qaeda leadership and he
was he was highly thought of in al-Qaeda
and he was very very good at logistics.
um that we knew that he knew everybody
who was worth knowing in al-Qaeda. He
knew cell leaders, he knew logistics
people, he knew finance people. We knew
that he was really one of the
intellectual leaders of the group. And
when you began to speak with him then
did you uh revert to Arabic?
>> No, he would never speak to me in
Arabic. And frankly, he was very polite
about it. We never exchanged a harsh
word. He was a he was an interesting
person to sit and have a conversation
with, but he would never speak to me in
Arabic. And his English was quite good.
>> It was fluent.
>> He was fluent in English.
>> He was.
>> And what was his demeanor?
>> He was a very, it's funny to have to say
it like this, but he was a very friendly
guy. Um, later on he did things like he
wrote poetry or he would debate uh the
merits of Islam or he would want to talk
about the differences or similarities
between Islam and Christianity. Uh he
wanted to talk about current events. He
he told us a couple of times that he had
nothing personal. There was nothing
personal against the United States. It
was Israel that he wanted to fight and
that the United States was close to
Israel and we had been caught up in
whatever it was that that bothered him
and uh he he he regretted having to help
plan attacks against Americans. But
because these were in the end attacks
against Jews and Israelis, it was
something that he felt he had to do. So
there was no attempt on his part to deny
involvement.
>> Oh no, not at all. Not at all. He was
quite open.
>> And did he talk about 911?
>> Yeah. He said that um that 9/11 was
necessary that although he didn't think
that there would be such a massive loss
of life, his view was that 911 911
rather was supposed to be a wake-up call
to the United States. It wasn't supposed
to be something that so shook the United
States that it led the US to attack uh
al-Qaeda's bases in Afghanistan. Um in
previous attacks, the USS Cole, the
embassy bombings in in East Africa, the
US government responded with missile
strikes against alleged al-Qaeda sites,
and they truly believed that that's how
we were going to respond to September
11th. They didn't think that there would
be an all-out attack. So they didn't
anticipate the death toll being so uh
large.
>> They didn't they didn't think the
buildings would collapse.
>> And that's what he told me.
>> As you began to talk to him, was time of
the essence? Did you feel you had to get
him to talk?
>> Yes. Because in the beginning, while
like I say, he was friendly uh and he
was willing to talk about philosophy, he
was unwilling to give us any any
actionable intelligence. And what in
your mind was your way you were going to
get him to give that up? We had a group
of folks uh at the agency who were
trained in uh what have been reported in
the press to be called enhanced
techniques. Um
I came back to the to the United States
to headquarters to move on to a
different job. But we had these trained
interrogators who were sent to his
location um to use the enhanced
techniques as necessary to get him to
open up uh and to report some threat
information. And can you describe them
>> in in generalities? I suppose I can say
that that my understanding is that
what's been reported in the press uh has
been correct in that these enhanced
techniques included everything from uh
what was called an attention shake where
you grab the person by the lapels and
shake them uh all the way up to the
other end which was waterboarding.
>> And that was one of the techniques.
>> Waterboarding was one of the techniques.
Yes.
>> And was it used on Zeta? It was.
>> And was it successful?
>> It was.
>> What happened as a result of that?
>> He resisted. He he was able to withstand
the water boarding for quite some time.
And by that I mean probably 30 35
seconds. That's quite some time.
>> Which was quite some time. Um and a
short time afterwards in the next day or
so he told his interrogator that Allah
had visit him in his cell during the
night and told him to cooperate because
his cooperation would make it easier on
the other brothers who had been
captured. And from that day on, he
answered every question just like I'm
sitting here speaking to you.
>> In a willing way.
>> So, in your view, the waterboarding
broke him.
>> I think it did. Yes.
>> And did it make a difference in terms of
>> It did. The threat information that he
provided disrupted a number of attacks,
maybe dozens of attacks.
>> No doubt about that. That's not some
hype.
>> No. No question. No question. The
reporting, I remember reading the
reporting and it was dramatic when it
first started coming in. Now, of course,
a lot of that was time-sensitive. So,
after a period of time, he wasn't able
to to provide any real actionable
information, any information that you
could use to disrupt an attack. But what
he was able to provide was information
on the al-Qaeda leadership. For example,
um if Bin Laden were to do X, uh who
would be the person to undertake such a
such an operation? Oh, logically that
would be Mr. Y. And we were able to use
that information to kind of get an idea
of how al-Qaeda operated, how it came
about conceptualizing its operations and
um and how it went about tasking
different cells with carrying out
operations.
>> And in terms of the actual planned
future attacks,
>> we disrupted a lot of them
>> and he knew about them.
>> He knew about some, but like I say, it
was time-sensitive information. So that
that wound down over time
>> and the ones that he knew about, were
they on US soil? Were they in Pakistan?
>> You know, I was out of it by then. I had
moved on to another job and I I don't
recall to the best of my recollection,
no, they weren't on US soil. Uh they
were overseas.
>> The fact that the interrogation
techniques had to go all the way to
waterboarding. That meant he resisted
the steps on the way to that. We've
reported the attention slap. Yes.
>> Uh sleep deprivation.
>> Correct. And I should add too that it
wasn't up to individual interrogators to
decide, well, I'm going to slap him or
I'm going to shake him or I'm going to
make him stay up for 48 hours. Each one
of these steps, even the the minor steps
like the intention shake uh or the
open-handed belly slap, each one of
these had to have the approval of the
deputy director for operations. So
before you laid a hand on him, you had
to send in a cable saying he's
uncooperative. Request permission to do
X. And that permission would come.
You're allowed to hit him one time in
the belly with an open hand.
>> It was that specific.
>> Cable traffic back and forth.
>> The cable traffic back and forth was
extremely specific. And the bottom line
was these were very unusual authorities
that the agency got after 9/11. No one
wanted to mess them up. No one wanted to
get in trouble by going overboard. So,
it was extremely deliberate. No one
wanted to be the guy that accidentally
did lasting damage to a prisoner or did
something to a prisoner without
authorization. It was very clear from
the beginning that this had to be done
within the rules. Was there concern that
it might kill him?
>> No. No. There was a doctor there and
none of these none of these techniques,
including waterboarding, was
life-threatening. an open-handed slap to
the belly or to the cheek uh wasn't
going to wasn't going to kill him.
>> Was there concern that the techniques
would result in false confessions? He
would just say something.
>> There was always that concern.
>> And how do you guard against that?
>> Well, the only way that you really can
at least partially guard against that is
to not do these things regularly. That's
why so few people were were
waterboarded. I think the agency has
said that two people were waterboarded,
Abu Zuba being one. And it's because you
really wanted it to be a last resort. um
because we didn't want these false
confessions, we didn't want wild goose
chases. One of the things that we were
able to do after a while so that you
wouldn't have to waterboard people is in
the beginning these prisoners were kept
isolated from one another and one didn't
know that the other had been captured.
So walking one past another's cell and
just allowing them to catch a glimpse of
one another was enough to shake them up
enough that they that they would begin
cooperating without you having to use
any of these enhanced techniques just to
see that one of his colleagues had been
caught.
>> That's right. And if you allow them to
believe that look, you've lost the good
guys won. You're all in jail. That was
enough to really turn the tables. And in
the case of Abdul Zaba, did you feel he
was broken emotionally, that he had felt
he'd lost the battle?
>> Yes. Yes, I think he did feel that way.
>> Okay. And in the end, it's funny, uh, a
a former colleague of mine asked him
during a conversation one day, "What
would you do if we decided to let you go
one day?" And he said, "I would kill
every American and Jew I could get my
hands on." And he said, "It's nothing
personal. You're a nice guy, but this is
who I am."
Did you feel comfortable with the
techniques? Uh, frankly, no. And I
elected to uh to forgo the training. I
was asked if I wanted to be trained in
the enhanced techniques. And I sought
the counsel of a senior agency officer
who's still an agency officer. And I
said, "What would you do in my
situation?" And he said, "Frankly, I
think it's a slippery slope. An
accident's going to happen and uh I
wouldn't do it." And so I declined.
>> So you did not go through the training?
>> I did not.
>> Have you seen waterboarding? Uh we
waterboarded each other in the beginning
to see what it felt like. Uh and it's a
it's a wholly unpleasant experience.
>> What is it like?
>> Uh you feel like you're choking or
drowning. And are you literally upside
down or
>> you're on your back with uh your feet at
a slight incline. Uh there's some
cellophane or material over your mouth
and then they pour water on this
cellophane. Uh you can't breathe and it
feels like the water is going down your
throat and then you begin choking it. It
uh induces the gag reflex,
>> but the water's not actually going into
your mouth or through your nostrils.
>> No, it just feels like it is.
>> It feels like it is because of the
pressure onto the onto the cellophane.
Correct. Like a saran wrap kind of
thing.
>> That's right.
>> And how long did you last?
>> About 5 seconds.
>> Really? There's Would you call it
torture?
>> Um,
you know, at the time, no. At the time,
I thought this was something that we we
really needed to do. I I had heard
stories of of captured German prisoners
from the Second World War playing chess
with their interrogators and over the
course of many weeks and months of
playing chess, they develop a rapport
and the German ended up giving
information. Al-Qaeda is not like a
World War II German P. It's a different
world. These guys hate us more than they
love life. And so they're not you're not
going to convince them that because
you're a nice guy and they can trust you
and they have a rapport with you that
they're going to confess and give you
their operations. It's it's different.
>> You're not going to be able to slowly
seduce them to talk.
>> Not these guys. And at the time I I felt
that water boarding was something that
we needed to do. And as time has passed
and has as September 11th has has, you
know, has moved farther and farther back
into history, um I think I've changed my
mind. And I think that uh waterboarding
is probably something that we shouldn't
be in the business of doing.
>> Why do you say that now?
>> Because we're Americans and we're better
than that.
>> But at the time, you didn't feel that
way.
>> At the time, I was so angry and I wanted
so much to help disrupt future attacks
on the United States that I felt it was
the only thing we could do.
>> And with Zaba, you think that was
successful?
>> It was.
>> And we have reported that Khaled Shik
Muhammad was also waterboarded. I was
out of it by then, but it's my
understanding that he was that he was
also water.
>> But those were really the only two
>> to the best of my knowledge. Yes.
>> And bottom line, as you sit here now, do
you think that was worth it?
>> Yes.
>> Did it compromise American principles or
did it save American lives or both?
>> It it I think both. It may have
compromised our principles, at least in
the short term. And I think it's good
that we're having a national debate
about this. We should be debating this
and Congress should be talking about it
because I think as a country, we have to
decide if this is something that we want
to do as a matter of policy. I'm not
saying now that we should, but at the
very least, we should be talking about
it. It shouldn't be secret. It should be
out there as part of the national
debate.
>> It's been revealed now that the CIA had
tapes of the interrogation underway.
Were you involved in the taping process?
>> No. In fact, I first learned about it in
the press yesterday. Do you were not you
did not see cameras? We had cameras
everywhere, but it was our understanding
at the time that they were closed
circuit cameras so that other
interrogators and medical personnel and
security officers could watch the
interviews uh taking place.
>> You didn't see it being recorded
anywhere?
>> No, I never saw it being recorded.
>> And now that you know it was recorded
and the tapes were destroyed afterwards,
>> what do you make of that?
>> I'm disappointed, frankly. I understand
that the AY's explanation was they
wanted to make sure that everything was
being done legally and within the uh the
guidelines that that the organization
had set forth, but it makes me wonder
instead if they simply didn't trust the
interrogators and if they wanted to
catch somebody doing something that was
unauthorized. So, frankly, I'm a little
disappointed that they didn't have that
trust in us. Having already been
polygraphed, having undergone, not me,
but other interrogators, having
undergone uh the training, they still
didn't trust us enough to uh to let us
do do our jobs.
>> You never saw tapes coming out of a
machine or being sent off to Washington?
>> No, never saw tapes.
>> And never reviewed them when you were
back in Washington?
>> No, never heard about them even.
>> Really? So, they were very closely held.
>> Very closely held.
>> Should they have been destroyed, do you
think? Uh, I think not. I think they're
a matter of uh of historical record, at
least within the agency. Uh, they may
have uh some legal import, and they
probably should not have been destroyed.
>> If we were able to look at those tapes
with Abu Zuba, what would we see?
>> I think you'll see a lot of very long
and very boring conversations about the
minutia surrounding the leadership of
al-Qaeda. I think you'll see a couple of
incidents where uh at least in the
beginning where he was um very tough and
uncooperative and then the rest of it I
think you'll see just a lot of open
conversations.
>> Will you see him being slapped?
>> You know, I have no idea if that kind of
thing was was taped. I would assume that
it was. So, you might you might see
something like that. If they tape the
enhanced interrogation,
>> we would see what
>> an open-handed belly slap maybe or
somebody who's very tired because he's
been up for 48 hours and not allowed to
sit down,
>> but kept much more than that.
>> Kept him standing for 48 hours
>> and do you suppose they taped the
waterboarding?
>> Gosh. Uh, I honestly don't know.
>> I don't know. If the American public was
to see somebody even Abu Zaba being
waterboarded, what would you guess would
>> I think it would be objectionable.
It it's it's sort of a violent thing to
to see or to go through. You may be of,
you know, one persuasion of the other
where you think it's a necessary thing
or or you think it's torture, but either
way you dice it, uh it it's not
something that's pretty to watch.
>> How does the body react?
>> Uh violently.
To me, it's almost like being shocked
where you tense up because you want to
you want to wiggle out of the way of the
water and you can't because you're
strapped down and and your head is
immobilized and you just have to lay
there and take it until the interrogator
stops pouring water on you
>> and the water's poured and you have a
kind of gag.
>> Mhm.
>> And you're just gagging.
>> Yes. You're gagging.
>> Correct.
>> Shouting or you can Can you do it?
>> Sure.
>> Mhm. and was a beta that was really only
354 seconds that
>> which was remarkable at the time because
none of us were able to withstand more
than 10 seconds worth 10 or 12 seconds.
He was quite tough I recall.
>> And you think that's what broke him
though?
>> I do. I do. I think he just didn't want
to go through it again. And if the
alternative is just sitting at the table
across from a guy with a notepad and
answering his questions, it's better
just to answer the questions.
>> And he decided to do that.
>> Yes. And was that considered a victory
inside the CIA? A big victory because
once the information started coming in
and we were able to corroborate it with
other sources uh and able to to uh uh
disrupt other operations, al-Qaeda
operations or terrorist attacks. That
was a big victory.
>> And who else was present at the
interrogation?
>> There were always several interrogators.
>> All CIA.
>> Uh all CIA. uh there was a doctor and
>> a CIA doctor
>> a CIA doctor and then once in a while
there would be um a substantive expert
like an analyst who was there to ask the
question somebody who really understood
the the details of what needed to be
asked uh who was there and just happened
to be around and asked to to stand in.
>> Were there FBI agents present at all?
>> It's my understanding that later on in
the process after I had moved on that
FBI agents participated as well. Not
necessarily in the waterboarding, but in
the interrogations.
>> We heard reports that the director of
the FBI instructed the agents not to be
involved in any
>> I'm sure that's true. Interrogation.
>> I'm sure that's true. Those authorities
that came from the White House to to do
the the enhanced techniques were solely
for the CIA, not for the not for the
FBI. So, it would make perfect sense to
me that the FBI director wouldn't want
FBI personnel around.
>> And did you and other CIA officers feel
without a doubt you had the legal right
to do what you were doing?
>> Absolutely. Absolutely. I remember I
remember being told when uh the
president signed the uh the authorities
that they had been approved uh not just
by the National Security Council but by
the but by the justice department as
well. I remember people being surprised
that the authorities were granted and I
remember uh one of the AY's senior most
leaders saying this is this is an
awesome responsibility that we have to
act within the confines of the law. this
isn't going to be something that's being
done willy-nilly that people are going
to be trained in it and we have to
follow this to the letter
>> and that was done.
>> Yes.
>> People were very very concerned at the
time about making sure that that no one
overdid it or no one overstepped the the
legal authorities. People were very
concerned.
So when the decision was made to first
do the slap of Abu Zuba, the permission
for that came specifically from
Washington.
>> Yes, absolutely. There was discussion.
It wasn't just a cable came in, can I
slap him? And the answer is yes, and the
cable goes back out saying yes. There
was discussion. Should we slap him?
What's to be gained if we slap him? Is
there going to be any fallout to
slapping him? Everybody talks about it.
The deputy director for operations says,
"Yes, you can slap him." The cable goes
out. They slap him, send in a cable
again saying, "We slapped him and this
is what happened." And if that works,
great. If that doesn't work, well, maybe
we shake him by the lapels the next
time. And you go through the whole
process again.
>> And it got to the point where you got to
sleep deprivation. He was standing up
for how long?
>> You know, I use that as an example, but
I'm I'm not sure to be honest with you
if they did the sleep deprivation with
him. Uh I I I don't specifically
remember that being used on him,
although it was one of the enhanced
techniques. It's possible, you know,
it's 5 and a half years after the fact
now. It's possible that that that was
skipped over in favor of waterboard.
>> So you didn't have to go through every
step?
>> No.
>> So if there was a time sensitive, you
could you could go right to it.
>> That's right.
>> And when the sleep deprivation was used
on others, uh was that effective?
>> It was effective. It was effective.
>> Why is why is that so effective? You
know, you may not think about it, but
but exhaustion is is a very difficult
thing to handle. It's one thing to be
tired. It's another thing to be so tired
that you begin to hallucinate. Uh, and
after a while, some people just can't
take it anymore. And they'll tell you,
if just give me an hour, give me two
hours of sleep, I'll tell you anything
you want to know.
>> Really?
>> Mhm. And that's after how long?
Generally,
>> I recall the handful of times it was
used on people. It was usually 40 hours
plus. They just simply couldn't take it
anymore.
>> And they'd be standing this whole time.
>> Mhm.
>> Falling over trying to
>> And you do things like you play music,
you talk to them, you make them walk
around so they they can't get
comfortable.
>> After Zubeta was interrogated and really
gave up all he knew, at least you all
you thought he knew about current
operations, what was his value then?
His value was
it allowed us to have somebody who we
could pass ideas on to for his for his
uh comments or analysis. For example, we
would say things like uh Mr. X was
arrested in some European capital and
the Europeans think he was going to
undertake such and such an operation.
Would he be the person to do something
like that? And Abu Zubir would say
something like, "Yes, he's the perfect
person." Or or yes, he had a he had a
specialty in bomb making, let's say, or
in weapons or in fake documents. Or
conversely, he would say, "No, that
doesn't make any sense. He didn't have
any experience in that area." Or, "You
should be looking at this other person.
This other person had experience in that
area." So, he was someone really to
bounce ideas off of.
>> He became a a resource in the sense of
sort of like a a double check.
>> Yes.
And you used him a lot like that.
>> Yes, we did. We used him a lot.
>> And at that point, was he completely
cooperative?
>> Completely cooperative,
>> but still hating the United States.
>> Yes. But like he said, it was nothing
personal. Uh
he's a Muslim and a Palestinian. He's
dedicated his life to the overthrow of
uh of Israel, the end of the existence
of Israel. The United States is on the
is on the side of Israel, and it's
nothing personal, but there's a war on
and he's on the other side. And what
happened to him? The initial
interrogation was done in Pakistan.
>> Now he was he was in such terrible
physical condition in Pakistan that
aside from a one or two minute
conversation that we would have every
four or five hours which was really
about nothing. Uh he he was uh
interviewed in in the uh the third
country that he moved on to from there.
>> Did he know where Bin Laden was?
>> No. No idea. hadn't seen Bin Laden in
six months, hadn't spoke to him in four
months, didn't have any idea.
>> And how about uh colleague Shik
Muhammad? Did he have a sense of him?
>> I was already gone by then. Um but my my
guess is no.
They're very stovepiped, very
compartmentalized
where almost no one knows where anyone
else is. Uh they have this system of
couriers that they use to communicate.
They're never on the they're never on
the phone
there. It's they're they're real pros.
>> He was moved from Pakistan, received
medical care in a third country, and how
long was he there? Was he continued to
be moved?
>> It was my understanding that that he was
moved a couple of times.
>> You know, I probably shouldn't really
say.
>> Okay. All right. One more question.
Okay.
>> Uh and but he continued to be and
continues to be a resource.
>> I've been out of the agency for a while
now, for almost four years now. Um when
when I left he he was still a good
resource to go to
>> and people were valuing what he said.
>> They were.
>> Was he ever caught in a lie?
>> No.
>> An exaggeration?
>> No. And we we really ran down everything
that he said. Obviously there are other
sources to to corroborate uh things. And
this is one way that you're able to vet
the people that you're speaking with.
And to the best of my recollection, he
never led us down the wrong path.
Were there any other u tricks of the
trade that you used to try to get him to
talk?
>> No, that was it. It was pretty
straightforward. And the reason why we
didn't use other tricks of the trade is
because those those tricks of the trade
require a great deal of time uh much of
the time and we didn't have that luxury.
We were afraid that there was another
major attack coming. We were afraid that
there would be an attack on US soil and
we felt that we really needed to get to
the bottom of what he knew quickly so we
could disrupt those those possible
attacks.
>> And were those fears realized? Do you
think there was in fact another major
attack?
>> I do.
>> I think al-Qaeda is always planning
another major attack. I think that this
is an ongoing battle that we're going to
be fighting for the next generation at
least and it's always going to be a game
of oneupmanship. We always have to have
information that is at least as good as
what they're planning. It's the only way
that we can that we can stop these
attacks.
>> Given that you felt that uh water
boarding and the enhanced interrogation
broke him if you if somebody else was
caught today,
wouldn't you want to use the same
techniques?
>> I think that I would be very tempted to
use the same techniques. I I
>> In other words, in your view, they they
do work.
>> I Yes, they do work.
>> No doubt about that. Like a lot of
Americans, I think I I'm involved in
this this internal intellectual battle
with myself,
weighing the idea that waterboarding may
be torture versus the quality of
information that we that we often get
after using the waterboarding technique.
And I struggle with it, I think, like a
lot of people do where, like I said
earlier, we're Americans and we're
better than this and we shouldn't be
doing this kind of thing. But at the
same time, what happens if we don't
waterboard a person and we don't get
that nugget of information and there's
an attack on a on a movie theater or a
shopping mall or or in Midtown
Manhattan, you know, at rush hour, then
then what do we do? I I would have
trouble forgiving myself.
>> We've reported that the director of the
CIA, Michael Hayden, has banned water
boarding, at least for now. Yes.
>> Hasn't been used.
>> Yes. and maybe since Khalishek Muhammad.
Did he make the right decision? Do you
think?
>> I think he probably did. I I think
>> I don't think it's permanently banned,
but for the moment it is.
>> For the moment it is. I think that we've
we've gotten up and running to the to
the extent that
we're we have enough information coming
in from enough different kinds of
sources that we do have a handle on on
al-Qaeda operations as they're being
planned at least right now and that
waterboarding is unnecessary.
you know, the the months after September
11th were different because we were we
were really reactive at the time, and we
were we were stunned by the by the
magnitude of of the attacks on September
11th, and we were afraid that something
of of equal um uh scope was was in the
works. And we were really trying to do
anything that we could to stop another
major attack from happening. And I don't
think we're in that mindset right now. I
think we're chasing them all over the
world. I think we've had a great deal of
success chasing them, not just by
ourselves, but with other with other
governments. And uh as a result,
waterboarding, at least right now, is
unnecessary.
>> And it's your view that al-Qaeda has
been foiled, that it wasn't because they
couldn't do it again, but because
>> efforts by the US and others stopped
them from
>> it disrupted them. Yes. There are
hundreds and hundreds of patriotic
Americans working for very little money
with no vacation and no sleep and no
time with their families, working in
horrible parts of the world just to make
sure that another attack doesn't occur.
>> Why did you leave the CIA?
>> Were you upset with yourself, what you
did?
>> No, I loved the CIA. I still love the
CIA. Uh but I'm a middle-aged guy. I
have four children and I wanted to spend
more time with my family and I thought
that you know there there's more to life
than just running to the four corners of
the earth on 6 hours notice to meet some
terrorist and uh I wanted to just spend
more time at